Guide to the Dickson H. and Marjorie B. Leavens Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Dickson H. and Marjorie B. Leavens papers
1904-1972
MS 715
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
(14 boxes)
The major portion of the papers of Dickson H. Leavens, economist and faculty member of the Yale Mission College in China, is made up of family and business correspondence. In the family correspondence, conducted regularly over nearly two decades (1909-1922), Leavens reports on the activities of the College and on political events in China, particularly in Changsha and Hunan. With his business correspondents, who were largely members of the Yale-in-China staff, the main subject is mission activities. The papers also include Leavens' writings on the economics of silver and essays on the history of Yale-in-China. The subject files largely concern the administration and finances of the mission (1902-1940). Marjorie Leavens's correspondence with her family and friends from 1915 and 1927 contains accounts of domestic affairs and her observations on Chinese life. Also in the collection are newspaper clippings and photographs of Changsha during the riots of 1910, Java, and Hong Kong.
Leavens, Dickson H.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Dickson H. Leavens, ca. 1940-1950; Marjorie Leavens, 1973; and Emily B. Visher, 1986.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series and one addition: I. Dickson H. Leavens: Correspondence with Family. II. Dickson H. Leavens: General Correspondence. III. Dickson H. Leavens: Subject Files. IV. Dickson H. Leavens: Writings. V. Marjorie B. Leavens: Correspondence. VI. Miscellany. Accession: 87-M-19
Scope and Contents
The Dickson and Marjorie Leavens Papers are arranged in six series: I. Dickson H. Leavens: Correspondence with Family; II. Dickson H. Leavens: General Correspondence; III. Dickson H. Leavens: Subject Files; IV. Dickson H. Leavens: Writings; V. Marjorie B. Leavens: Correspondence. VI. Miscellany.
Series I, DICKSON H. LEAVENS: CORRESPONDENCE WITH FAMILY, consists of letters written by Leavens to his parents and sisters Delia and Faith from 1909-1922. The letters, written almost weekly, give a detailed account of Leavens' day-to-day activities as a faculty member and treasurer of the Yale Mission College. They also contain Leavens' observations on political conditions in Changsha and Hunan, the Changsha riots of April, 1910, the revolution of 1911, and the student strike of June, 1919.
Series II, DICKSON H. LEAVENS: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, contains correspondence between Leavens and approximately ninety individuals, primarily members of the Yale-in-China Association staff, from 1909-1955. Correspondents of note include: Palmer Bevis, Rachel Dowd, Edward H. Hume, Kenneth Scott Latourette, Matilda C. Thurston, H. H. Vreeland, and Amos Wilder.
Subjects discussed include routine business and financial matters, mission activities, political conditions in Changsha, and personal news.
Series III, DICKSON H. LEAVENS: SUBJECT FILES, contains approximately forty reference files primarily relating to Leaven's activities as a faculty member and treasurer of the Yale Mission College.
Series IV, DICKSON H. LEAVENS: WRITINGS, contains copies of Leavens published and unpublished articles on the economics of silver and the history of the Yale-in-China Association. Among those relating to Yale-in-China history are: "The History of Yale-in-China" 1921-1922, "Memoirs of Yale In China" 1921-1922, and "Student Activities at Yali" 1913-1914.
Series V, MARJORIE B. LEAVENS: CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1972, is composed of letters between Marjorie Leavens and her family and members of the Yale-in-China Association staff. The bulk of the correspondence consists of Marjorie Leavens' letters to her family during the years 1915-1927 when she was living at the Yale Mission in Changsha. Subjects discussed include her day-to-day activities as a mission housewife, family matters, and her reactions to the Chinese people and culture.
Series VI, MISCELLANY, contains copies of Dickson H. Leavens' obituaries, newspaper clippings relating to his Yale-in-China Association activities, and fifty photographs. The subjects of the photographs are: Dickson and Marjorie Leavens, landscapes and urban scenes in Java and Hong Kong, and the damage done during the Changsha riots of 1910.
The major portion of the Dickson and Marjorie Leavens Papers was donated to the Yale University Library by Dickson Leavens in the late 1940s and early 1950s. In 1973 Marjorie Leavens donated further materials to the Yale Divinity School Library. These items were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in 1977.
Biographical / Historical
DICKSON HAMMOND LEAVENS, 1887-1955
Dickson Hammond Leavens, missionary, teacher, and economist, was born in Norwich, Connecticut, on March 16, 1887. After preparing at the Norwich Free Academy, Leavens entered Yale College as a member of the Class of 1909. Upon graduation he received a three-year appointment to teach English, history, and geography at the Yale Mission College in Changsha, China. Leavens returned to the United States in 1912 and studied mathematics at Columbia University and the Yale Graduate School, where he received his M.A. in 1915. Later the same year he married Marjorie Lathrop Browning of Norwich, Connecticut, and returned to Changsha, where he had received a joint appointment as treasurer and faculty member of the Yale Mission College. In the spring of 1921 he took a four-month leave of absence to aid in famine relief work at Paotingfu near Peking and in June returned to the United States on leave. During the summer of 1922 Leavens once again returned to Changsha and resumed his duties at the college. When the revolution of 1927 forced the closing of the Yale-in-China facilities in Changsha, most of the staff returned to the United States. Leavens, however, stayed on in Shanghai as the representative of the Yale-in-China Association's trustees. He was able to reenter Changsha in the spring of 1928 and make arrangements for the resumption of work with a Chinese staff.
After his return to the United States in late 1928, Leavens was employed as a research assistant at the Harvard Business School. He began a systematic study of the economic aspects of silver, a subject in which he had become interested while serving as treasurer of the Yale Mission College. In 1931 his first book, Problems in Business Statistics, was published. A second book, Silver Money, was published in 1939. From 1939 to 1936 Leavens served as a trustee of the Yale-in-China Association and during 1934 was employed as a Special Agent for the United States Treasury Department in China and India. In 1936 he was appointed a research associate by the Cowles Commission for Research in Economics. During the same year he became the editor of the Econometric Society's journal, Econometrica, which he edited until his retirement in 1948.
Dickson Leavens died on December 3, 1955, in Colorado Springs, Colorado.
*****
MARJORIE BROWNING LEAVENS, 1888-1977
Marjorie Browning Leavens was born in Norwich, Connecticut, on October 30, 1888. She graduated from Smith College in 1910 and later earned a masters degree in astronomy at Radcliffe College. In 1915 she married Dickson H. Leavens and accompanied him to Changsha, Hunan, where he had been appointed a member of the Yale Mission College faculty. While living in Changsha, Marjorie Leavens taught mathematics and astronomy at the Yale Mission College and encouraged the women of the city to develop a small cross-stitch embroidery industry. Returning to the United States in 1928, she lived with her husband in Cambridge, Chicago, and Colorado Springs, where she continued her interest in China by lecturing on her experiences in Hunan. She died on July 22, 1977, in Carmel, California.
Americans -- China; Missions -- China; Money; Asia; Changsha Shi (China); China -- Civilization; China -- Description and travel; Photoprints; Clergy; Economists; Educators; Missionaries; Beach, Harlan P. (Harlan Page), 1854-1933; Bevis, Palmer; Borden, William, 1887-1913; Dayton, Arthur Bliss, 1889-; Dowd, Rachel A.; Dunham, Harry J.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Gabriel, Ralph Henry, 1890-1987; Gage, Brownell, 1874-; Giles, Lancelot, 1878-1934; Holden, Reuben A. (Reuben Andrus), 1918-; Hosmer, John G.; Hume, Edward H. (Edward Hicks), 1876-1957; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Leavens, Dickson H.; Leavens, Marjorie Browning, 1888-1977; Lobenstine, E. C. (Edwin Carlyle), 1872-1958; Lovett, Sidney, 1890-1979; Morland, John Kenneth, 1916-; Nicholson, John B.; Rinden, Arthur Owen; Sallmon, William H., 1866-1938; Smith, Robert Ashton, 1914-; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Thurston, Matilda Calder, 1875?-1958; Vreeland, Herbert Harold, 1920-; Wilder, Amos Parker, 1862-; Williams, James Willard, 1885-; Ginling Association in America; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1909; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale-China Association
- DICKSON H. LEAVENS: CORRESPONDENCE WITH FAMILY, 1909-1922; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  DICKSON H. LEAVENS: CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE FAMILY is arranged chronologically.
  - 1909 January - 1913 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
  - 1914-1922 (Box 2, Folder 11-20)
- DICKSON H. LEAVENS: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1909-1955; Series II; 2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  DICKSON H. LEAVENS: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters of a particular correspondent are organized chronologically.
  - Achilles, Paul S. (Bachelor), 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Allen and Collins (architects), 1931 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Arnold, Lauren (Bachelor), 1931 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Atwater, Reginald M. (medical staff), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Beach, Harlan Page (Trustee, General Secretary), 1909-1911 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Benedict, Paul H., 1921 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Bevis, Palmer (Secretary-Treasurer), 1924-1928 January - June (Box 3, Folder 27-37)
  - Bevis, Palmer (Secretary-Treasurer), 1928 July - 1930 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
  - Borden, William W., 1909-1913 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
  - Cameron, Allen N., 1911 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Campbell, E. Fay (Trustee, Treasurer, Executive Secretary), 1930 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Carter, Gertrude P. (nursing staff), 1918 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Chaing, Louise, 1948, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Chandler, Robert E., 1931 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Chin, Alfred, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Chun Yen-So (student), 1911-1919 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Clark, Edwin N., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Coe, Richard Storrs, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Cooke, Forest, 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Cooke, Margaret, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Cooke, Norman V., 1918-1921 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Craighill, Marion J., 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Cross, Laura B., 1950 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Dayton, Arthur Bliss (Trustee, Vice-President), 1932 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Dodd, Allen R., 1928 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Dowd, Rachel A. (Recording Secretary, Assistant Treasurer), 1920-1923 September - December (Box 4, Folder 52-58)
  - Dowd, Rachel A. (Recording Secretary, Assistant Treasurer), 1924 January - 1945, 1947-1953 (Box 5, Folder 59-72)
  - Dunham, Harry J. (Business Manager), 1918 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Edwards, Betty L., 1954 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Farnam, Louise W. (medical staff), 1927 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Fisher, Irving, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Foster, John Hess (medical staff), 1928 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Gabriel, Ralph (Trustee, Vice-President), 1926 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Gage, Brownell (College Dean, Treasurer, Trustee), 1909-1921 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Gage, Nina (nursing staff), 1909-1910 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Gates, Frederick Lamont, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Gee, N. Gist (China Medical Board), 1927 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Giles, Lancelot (British Consul, Changsha), 1919 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Hadden, George (medical staff), 1917 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Hail, William J. (teaching staff), 1913-1919 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Harvey, Edwin D. (teaching staff), 1910-1921 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Holden, Reuben A. (Trustee, Secretary), 1950-1953 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Hosmer, John G., 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Hume, Edward H. (medical staff), 1909-1927 (Box 6, Folder 89-90)
  - Hutchins, Frank S. (teaching staff, Trustee), 1933-1935 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Johnson, Nelson T., 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Kelhofer, Mary and Ernest, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Latourette, Kenneth Scott (Bachelor, Trustee, President), 1915-1922, 1928-1930 (Box 6, Folder 94-96)
  - Lippitt, Henry, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Lobenstine, Edwin C. (Trustee), 1942 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Lovett, Sidney (Trustee), 1947 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Martin, F. C., 1926 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Matthews, Derrith, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Montgomery, James, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Morland, J. Kenneth (Executive Secretary), 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Morse, Oliver C., Jr. (Bachelor), 1912-1918 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Moyle, J. H., 1935 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Nicholson, John B. (United States Vice-Consul, Changsha), 1918 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Nightingale, Mrs. John C., undated (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Phillips, Andrew W., 1909 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Powell, Ralph W. (teaching staff), 1918-1921 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Reed, Edward Bliss (Executive Secretary, Trustee), 1909-1916 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Richards, Edward C. M., 1916 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Richards, Howard, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Rinden, Arthur O. (Executive Secretary), 1945-1956 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Roberts, W. P., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Sallmon, William H. (Assistant Treasurer, Executive Secretary), 1909-1913 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Seabury, Mortimer, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Shepard, Arthur Macartney, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Smith, George D., 1916 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Smith, Harold V. (teaching staff), 1915-1921 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Smith, Robert Ashton (Executive Secretary), 1940 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Smith, Robert G., 1940 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps (Trustee, President), 1913-1927 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Stuart, J. Leighton, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Swett, Raymond, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Thurston, Carl H. P., undated (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Thurston, Matilda C. (teaching staff), 1909-1918 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Torassian, Aram, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Tseng, Beanson, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Tyng, Walworth, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Vaill, George D. (Executive Secretary), 1954-1958 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Vincent, J. C. (United States Vice-Consul, Changsha), 1926 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Vreeland, H. H. (Trustee, Executive Secretary, Treasurer), 1922-1924 (Box 7, Folder 126-129)
  - Wang, Chengting T., 1910 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Wang, T. K., 1955 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Weigle, Luther A. (President), 1955 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Weigle, Richard D. (Bachelor, Executive Secretary, Trustee), 1933-1936 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Wheeler, W. Reginald (Executive Secretary, Trustee), 1916-1949 (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - White, W. C., 1921 (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Wilder, Amos P. (Trustee, Executive Secretary), 1914-1918 January - April (Box 7, Folder 136-139)
  - Wilder, Amos P. (Trustee, Executive Secretary), 1918 May - 1920 July - December (Box 8, Folder 140-146)
  - Williams, F. Wells (Chairman, Board of Trustees), 1911-1927 (Box 8, Folder 147-148)
  - Williams, James W. (Assistant Treasurer), 1909-1921 (Box 8, Folder 149-150)
  - Wilson, Stanley, 1916-1919 (Box 8, Folder 151)
  - Witt, Heinrich, undated (Box 8, Folder 152)
  - Wood, W. Herbert, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - Wright, Henry P., 1909 (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - Yen, Fu-Chun (medical staff) (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - Zee, Zai-Ziang (teaching staff), 1918 (Box 8, Folder 155)
- DICKSON H. LEAVENS: SUBJECT FILES, 1902-1940; Series III; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  DICKSON H. LEAVENS: SUBJECT FILES are arranged alphabetically by file title.
  - Accounting suggestions, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Accounting system: description of ledger accounts, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - American Consular Service, form letter re: facts exporters should know about Changsha, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Changsha riots: newspaper clippings, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Changsha University Club: abstract of constitution, undated (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - China Christian Educational Association: pamphlets, 1926-1930 (Box 9, Folder 161)
  - College accounting: correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 9, Folder 162)
  - Commonwealth equipment orders, 1923-1924 (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - Conference of Christian Colleges and Universities: correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - Conference on the support of the Hunan-Yale Medical College: report, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - Continuation Committee: memoranda and minutes, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - Depreciation reports, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - Extraterritoriality: newspaper clippings, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 168)
  - Finance Committee, Changsha: agenda and minutes, 1919-1925 (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - Finance Committee, New Haven: correspondence and minutes, 1920s (Box 9, Folder 170)
  - Frary Fund: correspondence, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 171)
  - Grocery orders to United States: correspondence, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 172)
  - "How a Chinese Family Lives on Three Dollars a Month" by Rose Elliott, Changsha, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 173)
  - Hunan Christian Educational Association: bulletins, 1923-1924 (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - Kuling: information pamphlet for visitors, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 175)
  - Leavens' bungalow: memoranda for occupants during furlough, 1921-1922 (Box 9, Folder 176)
  - Leavens' trip to Changsha; memoranda, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 177)
  - Mathematics Department: memoranda, 1916-1920 (Box 9, Folder 178)
  - Nanking Incident: newspaper clippings, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 179)
  - Notices to the Yale Mission staff, undated (Box 10, Folder 180-181)
  - Property records and debentures, 1920s (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Publicity Committee: minutes, 1918-1920 (Box 10, Folder 183)
  - Purchase of Chinese currency: memoranda, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 184)
  - Retirement plan for Yali Union Middle School faculty: memoranda, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 185)
  - Seabury Memorial Library: correspondence, 1907-1935 (Box 10, Folder 186)
  - Staff address list, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 187)
  - Staff charts, 1902-1928 (Box 10, Folder 188)
  - Staff party at Changsha: program, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 189)
  - Staff reunion, Norwich, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 190)
  - Staff reunions in the United States, 1921-1931 (Box 10, Folder 191)
  - Statistics Department: syllabi, 1907-1923 (Box 10, Folder 192)
  - Student lists, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 193)
  - Wanhsien Incident: newspaper clippings, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 193)
  - Yale Foreign Missionary Society, qualifications: memoranda, 1910-1912 (Box 10, Folder 194)
  - Yali Bachelor's Mess: correspondence, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 195)
  - Yenching University: bulletin (Chinese language publication) (Box 10, Folder 195)
- DICKSON H. LEAVENS: WRITINGS, 1910-1952; Series IV; .5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  DICKSON H. LEAVENS: WRITINGS are grouped together according to form.
  - Published articles, 1927-1952 (Box 10, Folder 196)
  - Unpublished speeches and sermons, 1912-1928 (Box 10, Folder 197)
  - Yale-in-China staff circular letters, 1910-1946 (Box 10, Folder 198)
  - Notebook showing distances from New Haven in great circles, with essay, "Names of Yale Men,", Undated, [1949?] (Box 10a, Folder 198a)
- MARJORIE B. LEAVENS: CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1972; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - 1908-1928 (Box 11, Folder 199-211)
  - 1930-1972 (Box 11, Folder 212)
- MISCELLANY, 1910-1956; Series VI; 0.25; (1 box)
  Materials in Series VI are grouped together according to form.
  - Dickson and Marjorie Leavens: obituary notices and biographical clippings (Box 11, Folder 213)
  - Photographs: Dickson and Marjorie Leavens; Yale Mission staff, 1915-1920 (Box 11, Folder 214)
  - Photographs: Changsha riots, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 215)
  - Photographs: Java and Hong Kong, 1920s (Box 11, Folder 216)
  - Photographs: Kuling and miscellaneous, 1920s (Box 11, Folder 217)
  - Yale-in-China memorabilia (Box 11, Folder 218)
- Additional Material, 1904-1971; Accession 1987-M-019; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Family, 1916, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - General, 1942, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany
    - Browning family, 1910-1913, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Personal, financial records, 1926-1927 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Photographs: Yale Mission Governing Board, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Yale memorabilia, 1904, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Subject files
    - Astronomy, Chinese, 1925, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Chang, K.S. family, 1956-1969 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - China, 1930-1966, undated (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
    - Famine relief, Paotingfu, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Ginling Association in America, 1949-1961 (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
    - Yale-in-China, 1913-1971 (Box 13, Folder 14-16)
  - Writings
    - General, [ca. 1933], undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Speech notes, 1940, 1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 18)